[music]
>> Joseph Smith
He's [music] someone I know well.
He's the author of a worldview that I
held for most of my life.
I taught it to [music] hundreds of
people when I was a missionary.
It's a religion and a gospel that I
deeply believed in.
One [music] full of hope and meaning and
community.
And unique stories.
>> [music]
>> Stories about where we came from and
where we're going.
Let me show you what Joseph Smith built
and how he did it.
How a non-religious, uneducated kid in
Upstate New York created a global
movement that would gather huge numbers
of followers in a very short time.
And who were pushed out from town to
town
often with violence.
I want to show you how these people held
on to the vision and mission that Joseph
Smith taught. The building of a new
utopian society. One founded on
celestial [music] laws. One that was
preparing for the end of the world and
the second coming of Jesus Christ.
So, let me tell you the story of Joseph
Smith,
>> [music]
>> the church he built, and how that church
and its mission still exist today.
That's okay. He's a missionary and
everyone's happy.
Joseph Smith was born in the perfect
place at the perfect time. It was the
early 1800s and the US had just thrown
off England to become a new country. It
was going through some massive growing
pains. Most of these new Americans who
had just left the old world rejected a
lot of old world things, namely
religion. Only 10% of white Americans
regularly attended church at this time.
So, to help revive God, you have all
these super charismatic preachers
[music] who left the cities and went out
to the countryside to preach. And this
led [music] to an explosion of religious
thought, especially in Upstate New York.
So now you have all these like hyper
reformist religions that were replacing
old style authoritarian type churches.
All these new wild religious flavors
[music] that were more emotional,
expressive, and personal. I mean, none
of us were alive at this time, but you
can kind of imagine like this brand new
country founded on these new ideals. It
[music] was unprecedented times. America
felt special and different, but also
kind of scary. Revolution in the new
world, new science, magical technology,
new ideas, both wholesome and sinful.
All of it speeding up at an increasing
rate.
For a lot of people this was a sign. A
sign that the end of the world was
coming and that Jesus, like he
prophesied,
>> [music]
>> would come back to usher in this
thousand years of glory for those who
believed in him and a thousand years of
fire for those who didn't. This was
called the millennium. So a lot of these
new churches that were cropping up kind
of claimed to be the place that was
preparing the [music] earth for the
second coming. Like they were God's
chosen administrators on the earth in
the final days before it all ended. It
was scary, it was exciting, and God was
talking to people again in new ways.
>> [music]
>> And this is the context that Joseph
Smith was born into in 1805. Born into a
mother who was swept up in the
excitement of all these new religions
>> [music]
>> and a father who wasn't really religious
at all. It's kind of like a lot of
people at the time, a family that was
religiously lost, but not for long.
>> [music]
>> In addition to being a frothy religious
environment, Upstate New York was also a
place where people hunted for treasure.
There was this culture of folk magic and
legends that led to the search for
riches and jewels that were potentially
buried by Spanish explorers or pirates
of the past or artifacts that were
hidden in Native American burial mounds.
And their methods for hunting for all
treasure were mystical and magical. They
used seer stones, crystals, rods,
visions through dreams, all of this to
help them [music] locate buried
treasure.
And young Joseph Smith was very caught
up in this treasure hunting craze. He
wasn't educated, he barely had any
schooling, he could kind of read and
write. [music] He wasn't religious,
but from a young age, he showed himself
as a skilled treasure hunter. I mean,
let's keep some perspective. In all of
our research, we didn't find a single
like document showing that he actually
found any treasure, but he managed to
convey to the people around him that he
was an expert treasure hunter using
mythical methods. So, this is the
context that you need to know to really
understand this story. We're in upstate
New York in the early 1800s, there is
this frenzy of folk magic and treasure
hunting, and the place is ablaze with
religious fervor. And there's talk of
the last days and the millennium of fire
and glory that was coming any day now.
But, the story really begins in the
spring of 1820.
>> [music]
>> Joseph, a 14-year-old boy, gets curious
about religion. And after visiting a
bunch of churches and finding no
answers, he decides to go into a grove
of trees to ask God which church was
true. This movie that we're watching
right now, I know by heart because I've
watched it hundreds of times, of course
dubbed in Spanish. I was a missionary in
Tijuana, and the first thing that I
would teach people was this story, and I
would often show them this movie. I
kneeled down
and began to offer up
the desires of my heart. So, Joseph
Smith [music] is in this grove, and he's
praying.
And after a running with the devil,
exerting all my strength to call upon
God,
>> [music]
>> he sees a pillar of light
brighter than [music] the sun directly
over his head.
And within [music]
that light he sees two people whose
brightness defy all description. He
finds out that it's God the Father and
his son Jesus Christ. And Jesus goes on
to tell him that none of the churches
that he's [music] been investigating are
true.
And that instead Joseph is being called
to do the work of God, to restore the
real true church that had been lost from
the earth, to restore this church to
prepare the world for the second coming
of [music] Jesus and the millennium that
he will usher in. This event is referred
to as the First Vision and it is the
founding story of the LDS Church, the
Mormon Church like most people know it.
As a member of the church from a very
young age you learn this story. You sing
about it, you talk about it, you study
it. And every few years the church
[music] comes out with a new video
version representing the First Vision.
>> [music]
>> Okay, so this is just the beginning. A
few years go by, Joseph doesn't tell
anyone about his vision, but by 1823
Joseph is a late teenager and one night
he's sleeping in his like little humble
cabin with his family and he says that
an angel appears to him. The angel is
named Moroni. By the way, if you ever
see a Mormon temple, big white building,
you will see a depiction of the angel
Moroni on the top of that temple with a
trumpet pointing east. But for now, he's
an angel in Joseph Smith's room telling
young Joseph that yes, the second coming
of Christ is right around the corner and
that yes, just like God and Jesus told
him a few years ago, he has been called
to prepare the world for the second
coming. And if that wasn't enough,
Moroni tells him that there is a book
that is written on golden plates that is
buried in a hill near Joseph's house.
The book is an important record of a
group of Jews who left Jerusalem in 600
BC and came to the Americas. Anyway,
I'll explain that in just a second.
[music] And don't worry, says Moroni,
along with the plates, there's the gear
you need to translate these plates into
English. Joseph just needs to get a bit
older and he'll be ready to translate
the plates. At this point, Joseph tells
his family what's been happening and
they believe him. So, by the time he's
21, he's instructed to go to the Hill
Cumorah near his house and get the
plates. Okay, so now Joseph Smith, in
his 20s, he's this uneducated,
unreligious treasure hunter and he
starts to focus in on something totally
new.
In the words of one believing Mormon
historian, Richard Bushman, he starts to
orient himself away from treasure and
towards [music] translation. He's
becoming a prophet.
>> [music]
>> So, Joseph says he goes and gets these
plates [music] and people try to rob
him, but eventually he gets them secured
and in a little cabin in rural New York,
Joseph begins the work
of translating this stack of metal
plates that no one else is allowed
[music] to see.
He would sit on one side of a curtain so
[music] that no one else could see.
And he says he looked through these
stones at the Egyptian engravings on
these golden plates and they would turn
into English. And then he would dictate
them out loud to a scribe, sometimes his
wife or other early believers who were
supporting him. And [music] that scribe
would write them down. At other points,
Joseph didn't even need the plates to
translate. He could hide them somewhere
else and he [music] would use his
personal seer stone, the one that he
used back when he was just a treasure
hunter before he says he was called as a
prophet, [music]
this little chocolate colored egg-shaped
stone. He would put it into a hat and
then he would bury his face in the hat
and he said that the stone would light
up with the words that he was supposed
to dictate to his scribe. His scribe
would write it down
and the Book of Mormon was [music] being
written. Now, listen, all of this seems
really weird and wild to us now, very
easily like, "Okay, clearly this guy's
making it up." But at the time, mystical
visions and treasure hunting and seer
stones, this was all very normal in
society. Folk magic, Native American
artifacts, none of this was very fringe.
And Joseph Joseph had been doing stuff
like this for a decade, which is why his
parents and [music] other people in his
community supported him. The difference
though at this time is that he was
blending his treasure hunting skills and
his folk magic sensibilities with this
religious revival that was happening at
the time to create something
kind of unique.
So, anyway, he's in his early 20s. He's
translating the Book of Mormon. He faces
a bunch of ups and downs. He goes
through a few scribes. And after a very
productive 90-day window, 24-year-old
barely educated Joseph Smith finishes
dictating 588 pages of text [music] that
would become the Book of Mormon.
Joseph says that he gives the plates
back to Moroni [music]
and then takes the manuscript of the
pages to a printer. That's how we have
the Book of Mormon. This is my Book of
Mormon.
Maps. [music] My early exposure
to maps.
So, the Book of Mormon is incredibly
important [music] to this story because
it was the main validator for Joseph
Smith in those early days and continues
to be a foundational part for believers
in the LDS faith. That's because Joseph
Smith wasn't religious or educated and
now suddenly he's writing this
Bible-like book in a few months. [music]
And yes, this book is definitely full of
a lot of like full-blown copy and paste
jobs from like the Bible.
>> [music]
>> But, there's also like a lot of really
compelling stuff in here in terms of
religious lessons, complex histories,
[music]
nods back to like an understanding of
Hebrew language and culture. This is not
[music]
the type of guy that his town saw him
as. He was a treasure hunter and a farm
kid, not a religious man and definitely
not a prophet.
>> Mr. Smith, could you tell me more about
that book?
Yes.
Yes, I could.
>> Okay, so let's be clear on what Joseph
Smith said the Book of Mormon is. It's
not what a lot of people say, which is
like the Mormon Bible. The book tells
the story of a group of Jews in
Jerusalem in around 600 BC. They're told
to leave the city before it gets
destroyed. So, they leave the city, they
walk in the desert for a while, probably
till like Oman is what a lot of Mormons
think, and then they build a boat and
travel across the ocean for a very long
time until they reach the Americas,
somewhere in like North, Central, or
South America. The foundation of the
story is about these brothers of the
original family who like eventually
split off and they like hate each other
and they grow up into these two
different civilizations, the Nephites
and the Lamanites, who are always
fighting with each other and there's all
these prophets and there's all this
drama that happens. And the introduction
to my Book of Mormon says,
the Lamanites, these people came over
from Jerusalem,
are  the principal ancestors of
the American Indians. And a few years
ago they did change that to the
Lamanites being among the ancestors of
the American Indians. But yeah, the
point is that the Book of Mormon is a
history of these Jews turned indigenous
Americans. And unsurprisingly, there's a
whole community of believers who work to
validate that [music] this is actually a
historic record. But no, in reality,
there's no archaeological, genetic, or
linguistic evidence that supports the
Book of Mormon's assertion that Jewish
people migrated to the Americas around
600 BC.
For believers, the most important part
of this book is the climax of the whole
thing where in 33 AD, Jesus, having
recently been crucified over in the old
world in Jerusalem, gets resurrected
over there and comes to visit the people
in America, which is where this painting
came from. This is a painting that is
hanging in a lot of LDS churches. It
shows Jesus Christ among the ancient
civilizations of the Americas.
Yeah.
Some pretty wild stories.
So, yeah. I know we're all over the
place and we'll get back to Joseph
Smith's life for a second. But, as
someone who has read [music] this book
dozens of times, I can tell you that
when you're a believer, this is a really
compelling piece of work. You can read
these pages. You can read about the
stories [music] and the lessons and the
metaphors. And you can take a lot from
it. And the biggest thing that you take
from it
>> [music]
>> is that it is proof that Joseph Smith
was actually called of God to prepare
the world for the second [music] coming,
that he was a legitimate prophet.
So, Joseph Smith, by 1830, has the Book
of Mormon. He has proof that he's a
prophet and he starts to gain followers.
Followers that believe him.
>> [music]
>> And a group of those followers get
together in April of 1830 in a little
house in Fayette, New York.
And they start a church.
At this point, Joseph Smith is behaving
like a full-blown prophet. He says he's
getting almost daily communication from
Jesus. And he starts to develop a
theology that is unlike anything else on
offer.
>> [music]
>> Turns out that God is actually a man
with a body of flesh and bone. And he
has a wife.
God lives
>> [music]
>> near a star that's far away.
And we, all of us here on Earth, are
these little eternal balls of light
called intelligences. But, our heavenly
parents have birthed us into spiritual
children. And then they sent us down
onto this Earth to get a physical body,
to get married, to create an earthly
family, to learn and to grow
so that someday we can return to live
with God with our families. [music]
And then we can become like God with our
spouses. We can create our own spiritual
families in some other part of the
universe. But in order to do that we
have to pass some tests here on Earth.
We have to complete certain rituals and
demonstrate obedience to him. And in
order to make this all happen he needs
to set up a church. The church needs to
have proper authority
>> [music]
>> and there would need to be a savior that
would come down to account for all of
our sins so that we can be pure to enter
the kingdom of God again. Luckily, one
of our spiritual brothers named Jehovah,
later called Jesus, volunteered to be
this savior.
>> [music]
>> Okay, but there's a big problem which is
that God's children are super
rebellious. So, over the years God calls
prophets to organize his church with the
proper authority and to do all of these
special rituals to teach them about
Jesus. And eventually that truth gets
eroded and it fades away and the world
falls into apostasy until it's ready
again when God calls another prophet to
restore his authority and start the
whole process over again. This happens
over and over until eventually Jesus
came. He was like the sixth prophet.
[music] He establishes his church, calls
his prophets and apostles, gives them
the authority by putting his hands on
their head, and then of course he
suffers for our sins and dies on the
cross. But just like it's happened over
and over Jesus' church got corrupted.
[music]
It got mixed with power and politics and
the world fell back into the apostasy.
This one's called the great apostasy.
[music]
But eventually the world would be coming
to an end.
Jesus would be coming soon [music] and
things were about to get really bad. So,
God helped Europeans come across the
ocean to take over North America,
colonize the land, and create a country
that had freedom of religion. Also, that
a few decades later Joseph Smith could
be born and then called to restore his
church. And that's how we get to the
first vision. [music] Jesus and Heavenly
Father appearing to Joseph Smith in a
grove, sending angels to him to tell him
where to get the golden plates. And
[music] to solve for the whole authority
thing, Joseph says that the apostles,
the original apostles of Jesus Christ
came [music] to him to restore the
authority, the priesthood, that Jesus
had given them. So, now he could
establish his church. There was a
restoration. Joseph was the prophet of
the newly restored church that [music]
he could talk to God. He could get
instruction on exactly how to run God's
kingdom here on Earth to prepare the
world for the millennium.
Okay, that was a lot. And let me just
say that was a very summarized version
of LDS theology. Someday I'd like to
make a video about the details because
it's actually super complex and super
wild. The point I'm trying to make here
is that Joseph Smith's church did indeed
have a lot of the ingredients of the
religious movements of the time. Last
days, apocalypse, preparing God's
kingdom on the Earth, preparing for the
millennium. This was all trending at the
time. [music] This was not surprising.
But, a lot of this stuff was totally
new, wild, fringe doctrine. God has a
body and a wife? This was a completely
wild blend of Jewish mysticism, American
folk magic, reincarnation, Evangelical
Christianity, and eventually he even
wove in Freemasonry. A totally fresh
thing. There was nothing quite like it.
It was super unique and super potent and
super polarizing. You either believed
that Joseph Smith was an incredibly
inspired prophet who was like revealing
the truth that none of us had ever heard
before, or he was just a brilliant
creative visionary inventing this
elaborate plan to dupe people, which is
what a lot of people in his village
started to think as he started to gain
followers. They had him arrested,
calling him a disorderly person. He
eventually gets released, and he
realizes that he and his few members
need to leave.
>> [music]
>> This begins the long journey of the
Mormons moving west.
>> [music]
>> Joseph and his followers set out. He's
now talking to God directly all of the
time, and he says that the Lord is
telling him to go to Ohio to await
instructions [music] for their actual
final destination, the place that
they're actually going to set up their
new city, their millennial kingdom, this
communal utopian society [music] that
would be the base for preparing the
world for the second coming of Jesus.
They would [music] call it
Zion.
>> [music]
>> And this is the most important part of
the entire story, Zion.
If you want to understand [music] Joseph
Smith, and if you want to understand the
rest of the Latter-Day Saints movement,
including modern Mormonism, [music]
you have to understand Zion.
>> [music]
>> Joseph says that the Lord is telling him
that he will give [music] him the exact
location of Zion. And he tells him that
it will be, quote, "on the borders by
the Lamanites." Remember that the
Lamanites are the American Indians, and
so this actually [music] works perfectly
because at this time the US government
is ethnically cleansing North [music]
America and pushing first Americans
west. So, there's a lot of territory
where white settlers are budding up
against Native Americans. [music]
Zion's going to be somewhere around
here. So, Joseph and his followers are
now in Ohio, and they are growing.
People love this story, and the concept
of Zion transitions from this sort of
vague idealistic idea to a very solid
plan, a new society called the New
Jerusalem, the New Jerusalem from the
prophecies of old. And it literally
became a plan. Like he actually starts
to sketch it on paper.
We got these digital scans of Joseph
Smith's sketches of Zion.
>> [music]
>> He writes in extreme detail on exactly
what this city will be. This whole thing
was based on these gridded streets, on
perfectly parceled plots on no more than
1 square mile of land. Joseph writes
that the home should be 25 ft from the
street to leave room for a yard and
plant gardens. All the houses were to be
brick or brick and stone. And there
should be farms all around this city
that aren't too far. The central streets
of this city nod to Joseph's love for
Jewish history and culture. Zion Street,
Jerusalem Street, Bethlehem Street, with
the temple in the center of the city.
Spoiler alert, this is how Salt Lake
City and a lot of cities in Utah are
actually designed, but that's for part
two. I mean, what this shows is that
Joseph was taking this idea of God's
restored kingdom on Earth totally
literally. And it was going to be hyper
progressive, a new communal society
where everyone would share with one
another. The resources would be shared
and the whole thing would be governed by
celestial laws and governmental
structures. [music] A new government run
by the prophet, where God could talk to
his people while he prepared the world
for [music] its end. Zion was a vision
that Joseph was uniquely good at
rallying [music] around. Charismatic
creative leader, prolific and inspiring,
his followers became deeply dedicated to
this mission of establishing [music]
Zion. And it becomes the main calling
card for new converts. Joseph Smith's
millennial kingdom is the place to be
when the world ends, and the world's
ending any day now.
>> [music]
>> So the church is growing in Ohio. They
still don't know where the final
location of Zion is going to be. And
meanwhile, Joseph is getting more and
more and more of these revelations, and
he's pushing the belief system of
[music] Mormonism further and further
from mainstream Christianity. Joseph
comes out and says there actually is no
heaven and hell, but rather there are
three kingdoms of heaven. All of us will
be sorted into these different [music]
kingdoms depending on how obedient we
were here on Earth.
How much we accepted Christ and repented
of our sins. There's even a spiritual
prison and paradise that you go [music]
to after you die, but before you're
sorted into the kingdoms. In order to
get to the highest degree of kingdom,
the celestial kingdom, you have to be
married by the proper authority that
will seal you to you and your family
forever. And soon, Joseph says that more
angels are appearing to him to give him
the authority to do this sealing thing.
Family is becoming core to Mormon
[music] theology.
But the good times don't last.
The locals in Ohio and their government
don't love this vision of a new
religious society. The flocks of new
members of the church arriving to this
super well-organized, efficient, unified
group of people led by this charismatic
prophet who has more and more fringe
beliefs. One night, Joseph is violently
dragged from his home by a mob. He's
covered in tar and feathers.
They're telling him to leave, and he
does. Luckily, one of Joseph's
missionaries and former scribes, Oliver
Cowdery, had been out scouting where
Zion should be, where the millennial
kingdom should be set up. And he comes
back and says he found the place,
Jackson County, Missouri, 800 miles
away.
Indeed, and [music] just as the Lord
said, right on the border with the
Lamanites.
This would be Zion, the Lord tells
Joseph, the place where he has appointed
for the gathering of [music] the saints.
And now there's a revelation from the
Lord saying that all of this land in
Independence, Missouri should be
purchased by the saints. Buy up as much
land as you can. This is [music] Zion.
Oh, and it is revealed to Joseph that
this area, Independence, Missouri,
Jackson County, Missouri, is right next
to the original Garden of Eden. Like
where Adam and Eve, like the first
people were. Turns out that Missouri is
like the holy land. The epicenter for
the end of the world and the Garden of
Eden is in Missouri.
So, Mormons start buying up land and
they start moving to Missouri. And they
did this quickly. This wasn't
theoretical. They thought that the
second coming was like weeks or months
or just maybe a few years away. Martin
Harris, one of the early converts,
asserted that, quote, "In four years,
every religion in the US would be broken
down and all would become Mormon and
that the rest of the human race would
just perish." And then he was so
confident that he said that if it didn't
happen, he would cut off his own hands.
I mean, they were serious about building
Zion in Missouri and quick. Okay, but
not so fast. The locals
like are not into this. They hear about
this swarm of Mormons coming to their
county who want to turn their city into
a new religious communal society and
prepare for the apocalypse.
>> [music]
>> And now they're arriving by the
thousands, which means they will have
more political power soon. They start to
get scared that the Mormons are plotting
[music] a takeover of their private
property all in the name of building
Zion and they're not going to stand for
it. They want the Mormons out. So, they
start sabotaging them with violence,
vandalizing their stores, destroying
their homes, assaulting Mormon leaders.
It gets really violent. And at first,
Joseph tells his followers to not fight
back. And once again,
the Mormons are driven out.
>> [music]
>> The next five years are years of
conflict for Joseph and his growing
church. They're on the move all over the
Midwest. At each stop, facing violent
resistance from local residents and
government officials. So, Joseph and his
followers are done being passive.
[music] They start fighting back, and it
escalates into basically a full-blown
war. The governor of Missouri issues a
literal extermination order saying,
"Quote, the Mormons must be treated as
enemies and must be exterminated or
driven from the state if necessary for
public peace." It's getting really bad.
So, they flee once more to Illinois,
where the government, who includes a
young lawmaker named Abraham Lincoln,
[music]
gives them a special charter to create a
city and a government that is fit for
their unique Zion principles. [music]
They call this city Nauvoo, Hebrew for
beautiful or beautiful place.
>> [music]
>> Okay, so even though the Lord had said
to Joseph that he had prepared Missouri
to be the place for Zion, the Saints
were going to have to settle for
Illinois for now. And they feel safe,
protected by this charter, and they
start creating Zion. There's a total
merger between church and state, a
complete religiously run settlement
where Joseph appoints himself to be in
charge of the courts as well as the
newly strengthened militia. They now
have a full army to protect [music]
themselves. Joseph had been sending
missionaries to Europe to preach about
the gospel and invite people to come
join his vision of Zion. And one of
those people is my like
great-great-grandfather
who was converted by a missionary in
England and then traveled to the United
States with his family and pregnant wife
in pursuit of finding Zion. And they
arrived to Nauvoo,
a city that eventually grew to be more
populous than Chicago. And it's in
Nauvoo where Joseph says that an angel
appeared to him and demanded, multiple
times against his will, that he take on
multiple wives, that those wives are
sealed to him. His first plural marriage
is to a teenager, and he goes on to have
40 wives in just 3 years. Many of them
were married to other people, but then
were sealed to Joseph the prophet. What
I find striking here is that up until
this point, you have this meticulous
documentation of every single revelation
and theology rule and new policy in the
church here in what's called the
Doctrine and Covenants. But polygamy
stayed quiet and [music] private. It was
one of those revelations reserved for
just Joseph and the leaders that he
chose.
>> [music]
>> By 1844, the Zion dream is actually
catching fire. It's growing in Illinois
>> [music]
>> and Joseph decides to run for president.
Now, he didn't have a big chance of
winning, but in his mind [music] and the
mind of his followers, this was the
natural next step. They were
establishing Zion and Zion was going to
be
>> [music]
>> the new society on Earth. But this
presidential campaign miserably
backfires because now [music] he is seen
as a legitimate political threat. He's
too good at gaining new followers. It
gets worse when one group of former
Latter-day [music] Saints who didn't
agree with Joseph decide to publish a
newspaper in Nauvoo that criticized
[music] him for polygamy and generally
his leadership. Joseph is done messing
around at this point. He's become
[music] very militant and he responds by
sending his militia to destroy their
printing press. [music] He declares
martial law and now the government of
Illinois who had given them this sort of
safe charter sees this chaos and they're
not into it. And they arrest [music]
Joseph for attempting to incite a riot.
Now, this was one of many run-ins with
the law that Joseph Smith had in cover
them. Some of them were legitimate, some
of them were trumped up, but now he's
caused a real disruption. He gets locked
up in jail and two days later, a mob of
more than 200 men storm this [music]
jail. They climb up to the second floor
where Joseph and his brother are and
they shoot at him. He tries to jump out
the window
>> [music]
>> and he falls to his death.
The prophet is dead at 38.
Joseph Smith is now a martyr. He died
with a Book of Mormon in his hands
defending his vision, his belief, and
his own [music] story.
This poured fuel on the fire of his
vision for Zion. [music] But the
Latter-day Saints start to realize that
if they're going to build Zion, it's not
going to be in [music] the United
States.
They need to look further afoot. They
need a place far away where they can
build their millennial kingdom without
being harassed for it. So they look
[music] far to the west to Mexico. And
the next chapter of the story is the
move into Mexico and the establishment
of their Zion [music]
next to a large salty lake in the high
desert. And that is a story I'll tell
you in part two.
But for now, I want to just tell you my
thoughts on Joseph Smith. As someone who
spent most of my life believing this
story, basing my life and my worldview
around it, doing this story and looking
at it from an objective historical lens
has taught me a lot.
>> [music]
>> Joseph Smith created something really
powerful. You can't deny that. It was a
story about the last days. [music]
It was a story full of treasure and
visions and angels and modern-day
revelation from God. It was a story
about a chosen people,
a utopian society of one heart and one
mind,
safety,
enlightenment. There's a reason why
every year Latter-day Saints go back to
that hill in state New York where Joseph
said he found the plates, and they put
on this insanely [music]
ambitious production on a stage that's
like 10 levels deep with almost [music]
a thousand characters where they reenact
the story of Joseph Smith, their
prophet. They reenact him finding the
plates, translating [music] them, and
then they act out the story of the Book
of Mormon. There's a reason why
Latter-day Saints sing a song called
Praise to the Man where they laud Joseph
Smith, the prophet who opened the last
dispensation, who restored the truth to
[music] the world.
I believed this. I believed this well
into my 20s. I found deep comfort in
[music] it. I found community and being
a part of a religion that was so
different than every other religion and
that was very often mocked for it.
>> [music]
>> The martyrdom and the persecution of
Joseph and his followers became proof
that this was true and that it was
[music] being persecuted in these last
days just like the prophecies in the
Bible told us about.
And I was compelled by this [music] idea
of the last days. The problem with
getting caught up in
the beauty and the comfort and the
narrative of being a chosen people in
the last days is that
it allows you to ignore.
I think that's what a lot of people have
done over the decades [music] with
Joseph's story. They ignore. They ignore
something that I guess is plain for me
to see now on the other side of this.
>> [music]
>> Brother,
I am a happy
happy man.
I've been on a mission for more than
[music] a year now. I can relax.
Joseph Smith was a charismatic [music]
leader who knew how to tell stories
about magic, about visions and about
treasure. [music]
He had known how to do that since he was
a teenager, well before he decided he
was [music] going to become a prophet.
He found an audience in doing this. He
attracted people to him with his
visionary skills.
And he used [music] those skills to
invent a complex set of stories about
Native Americans actually being
Israelites, about heavenly parents
[music] preparing the world for its end,
and about the priesthood, this authority
that we all must participate in [music]
to receive the rituals and ordinances
that only one church can administer. And
eventually he [music] used these stories
to build a movement around his vision
that allowed him to take 40 wives and
build an army and break laws [music]
and bully his enemies. When you are a
Latter-Day Saint, these facts [music]
are written off as anti-Mormon
literature or persecution, but for me,
having left the church and
>> [music]
>> spent years rewiring my brain and my
programming of these stories, I see them
as facts.
>> [music]
>> And frankly, they're not that
surprising. This is the same old story
of a charismatic visionary man who tells
a story of apocalyptic [music] endings
to gain followers, to gain power, and
then decides that he deserves a lot of
women,
>> [music]
>> and then he dies for the cause, leaving
a movement that continues his vision.
Often times those movements get more and
more dogmatic. [music] They use shame to
keep their people close to them,
and
they revere [music] their prophet
long after that prophet is dead. And
yet, what's complicated about this is I
can't help but feel a deep sense [music]
of sadness for having lost my belief in
Joseph's story.
I can't explain [music] it,
but these stories are incredibly
comforting when you believe in them.
They are motivating.
>> [music]
>> These creative stories, unlike any other
belief system,
can be really beautiful. And that is a
paradox
that there's really [music] no
resolution for. There's a lot more to
say on this, but I'm going to save it
for part two on the series where we see
what happens next after Joseph is
murdered and the Latter-Day Saints move
west to find their vision of Zion.
>> [bell]
>> Okay.
All right, quick pause. Because if you
love coffee or you want to explore the
world of coffee, I have a very cool
product [music] for you.
You see, I grew up Mormon, so I didn't
drink coffee until my late 20s.
>> [music]
>> And since starting to drink coffee, I've
started to really enjoy specialty
coffee.
>> [music]
>> Tasting different coffees from around
the world and exploring the different
flavors and profiles to find out what I
like best.
But the more I got into this, the more I
learned that much of the coffee we drink
[music] is the opposite of specialty.
Stale beans that lost their flavor weeks
ago, burned and brewed into plastic and
sold at mass volume. Providing a truly
delicious global journey of high-quality
coffee is why our sponsor Cometeer
[music] made this, the World Mug
Collection Box. And honestly, I'm very
stoked that this box [music] exists.
Seriously. In here, you get 32 cups of
premium coffee from 16 different
countries around the world. [music]
They're sourced from specialty roasters,
perfectly brewed, flash frozen, and
ready to make at home in minutes.
>> [music]
>> You can taste them head-to-head, like a
global coffee bracket, and find out
which one's your favorite. Right now,
I'd say my favorite cup of coffee in
this box is this one. [music] It's a
medium roast from Australia called Ghost
Writer. And I can actually tell that it
[music] tastes different from the
others, and I genuinely like it more.
Making a Cometeer cup of coffee is
ridiculously easy. Just melt this
capsule with hot water or melt it and
mix it for iced coffee or for lattes.
The flash freeze process locks in all of
the flavor that is extremely difficult
to get at home. And [music] even better,
there's no machine, no grinder, no
plastic waste to worry about. I've been
drinking Cometeer coffee here in the
office for literally years, [music] and
I love it. So, if you like coffee or you
want to start to explore the world of
coffee, [music]
you should start with the World Mug
Collection Box from Cometeer while it's
available. Use the link in my
description and you'll get $20 off your
first order from Cometeer.
>> It started with the murder of their
prophet in Illinois. [music]
Joseph Smith,
leader of 26,000 Mormons, father to 14
children, husband to 40 wives.
>> [music]
>> The prophet, seer, and revelator was
dead, and the Mormons were under attack.
So, they fled. [music]
They found safety in the mountains of
Mexico, where they would go on to build
their own utopian [music]
society,
building the promised land with its own
language, symbols, [music] government,
and economy. And a new prophet speaking
for God, leading the church's growth,
taking 56 wives of his own, and
continuing Joseph's vision of building
Zion in the mountains.
>> [music]
>> Here in the wild west, the Mormons would
go on to draw this shape as the borders
for a state of their own,
>> [music]
>> something that would lead them into a
war with the United States government,
nearly destroying everything they had
built.
It's a conflict that helped build the
west, [music] and it certainly shaped
these people, eventually shaping me, the
[music] stories that I heard, the
culture that I grew up in, the
university I attended, the way I saw the
world.
>> [music]
>> This is a complicated and sensitive
topic, and as always, my sources are in
a document in the description. Please
scrutinize and critique them if you
don't agree. I look forward to an
interesting discussion in the comments.
With that, let's dive into part two of
the rise of the Mormon church.
Watching part one of this series will be
helpful if you're unfamiliar with Joseph
Smith or the establishment of the Church
of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints or
the Mormon church. This is part two, and
we're starting in the 1840s, when
[music] the Mormons are kicked out of
Illinois and Missouri and they make this
1,000-mile grueling journey into what
was then the remote mountains of Mexico.
Your forefathers and mine came to this
country in the first place for one great
reason, to escape persecution for their
beliefs and to build a free country
where everybody might worship God as he
pleased. Yes, all of this was [music]
Mexico for a very long time. The Mormons
believed and still do believe that
someday they would return to the sacred
land of Jackson County, Missouri, where
they would help usher in the end of the
world and the second coming of Jesus
Christ. But for now, they would build
Zion in the mountains of Mexico, far
away from the American government and
people.
>> [music]
>> Or at least, so they thought. And this
is where things get really interesting
to me, because right after the Mormons
arrive to these mountains, they start
building. And they start building fast.
They used the same designs that Joseph
Smith had drawn up for the city of Zion,
placing the holy temple at the center.
Around this temple, they would build
their city as a perfect grid. [music]
But what's most impressive to me is how
well they cooperated [music] and
coordinated with each other, how
motivated they were, how industrious and
productive they were. They worked
tirelessly for their vision of Zion.
[music] And this became a core part of
the Mormon identity. They ended up
adopting the beehive as [music] a
metaphor for their community, a group of
industrious, highly motivated people all
working together for a common goal.
According to the Mormon scriptures, the
Book of Mormon, there's an ancient
[music] word for honeybee. That word is
Deseret.
>> [music]
>> And Deseret would soon be the name of
their proposed state. And it became a
foundational symbol for these people
building their Zion in the mountains of
Mexico.
Okay, but they didn't just build one
city next to Salt Lake. Very soon after
arriving, Brigham Young sent members of
the church north and south to repeat the
same pattern, to find an area to build
it up quickly with the same grid design,
putting the temple in the middle, and
begin developing and settling this land.
[music]
In a very short time, the Mormons spread
throughout [music] this mountain west
area, building a network of settlements
and displacing native people in a lot of
cases. Sometimes peacefully with
treaties, but other times with violence.
I can't emphasize enough how industrious
these people were. They were doing
things that no one else was doing out in
the west. They were building
sophisticated ditches and canals and
reservoirs, getting water into this arid
land so that they could farm and grow.
[music]
They were mining metals. They were very
productive, and then they would share
their surplus with one another because
in their mind, Zion was a place of
[music] one heart and one mind. There
would be no poor among them. The
community was more important than the
individual.
Which was the complete opposite of what
most settlers were thinking and doing in
the American West at the time. Shortly
after the Mormons arrive, 1848, thanks
to a victory against Mexico, the US gets
all of this land,
>> [music]
>> which places the Mormons back inside the
borders of the United States. But still,
the government didn't have a lot of
control out here. This was still the
wild west. Most people coming out here
were white settlers in search of a new
life, pursuing their dreams of freedom,
of abundant land, of riches and gold out
in the wild west. And right in the
middle of all of this, this group of
industrious Mormons, driven by obedience
and sacrifice [music]
and a commitment to communal living,
preparing for the end of the world, for
the millennium. This is a tension that
will blow up in just a second. But
first, we need to talk about how popular
the Mormon Zion was becoming.
>> [music]
>> Brigham Young had sent missionaries all
over, but especially to Europe, to
[music] the west coast of England
specifically, where these missionaries
would preach the word of the restoration
of the gospel and the building of Zion
in the American West. And it really was
effective. When I was a Mormon
missionary in Mexico, we would hear
stories about these Mormon missionaries
out in England who were doing this
initial missionary work. And honestly,
these guys were like legends to us. They
were so successful. [music] The Mormons
back in Salt Lake would pool their money
together and help pay for the way of
these new converts across the ocean,
across the continent to come join
[music] them in building Zion. My great,
great, great grandmother and grandfather
were some of these converts from Wales.
They were converted by a missionary in
Wales and then made the grueling trek
with their children, eventually ending
up north of Salt Lake City, [music]
where they contributed to building Zion.
So, for me and a lot of people who grew
up with pioneer heritage, as we call it
in the church, [music] these stories of
sacrifice become a foundational part of
our belief and our faith. Why else would
our ancestors have sacrificed so much
>> [music]
>> to build this church?
Brigham Young's Society of Worker Bees
started to become more than just a
religious community [music] in the
mountains. They were starting to look a
lot more like a theocratic society with
the prophet as the head of their
government. They had schools, they had
newspapers. Their network of settlements
created a complex economy that was
[music] run by the church, who directed
everything, where to build, what to
build. Soon, they had their own
currency. [music] They made these really
unique coins, some featuring their
unique symbols, handshakes and a
reminder that union is strength. Or,
here we see [music] the beehive again,
and a reminder to do your duty. They're
building sugar mills and processing iron
and building factories, and they even
invented their own writing system, like
their own alphabet, which was meant to
unify the people around a common way to
spell and pronounce words. I actually
have a reprint here of the Deseret
alphabet. [music]
They never taught us how to read this,
which I'm kind of bummed about because I
would love
to know what this all says.
But, there was a big problem for the
Mormons, which is that this was all now
the United States, and the federal
government was exerting more and more
control west as more and more people
settled out there. Once again, this
could be the end of the Mormon's vision
of Zion. So, they acted very quickly and
decided to propose a state of their own,
telling the government that, "Hey, we
know you didn't like us settling in
Missouri or Illinois, but we're out here
in the west and we've settled and
developed all of this land in a really
short time. Please let us have our own
state so that we can practice our
religion as we please." And what is the
state that they proposed? This massive
shape.
>> [music]
>> Take a moment to soak this in. Look at
where we are here. These borders for the
proposed Mormon state encompass parts of
modern-day Arizona, Southern California,
Colorado, Idaho, New Mexico, Oregon,
Wyoming, and Utah. This thing is huge.
If it had become a state, the modern
United States
>> [music]
>> would look something like this, bigger
than Washington, Oregon, and California
combined, and they would [music] call it
the State of Deseret. They were serious.
They drafted [music] a constitution, and
they lobbied hard for their state. And
the US government said, "Absolutely not.
Of course not." The government didn't
love that the Mormons were building this
theocratic society that was completely
independent from the United States. But,
they did kind of like how industrious
the Mormons were, how effective they
were at settling this land, displacing
the natives, and building up communities
for white people. This is something the
United States was doing at the time. It
was their manifest destiny, and the
Mormons were really good at it. So, in
order to keep the Mormons productively
settling the land that they had just won
from Mexico, the federal government does
grant them this territory. Not as big as
the state of Deseret, but still a nice
big territory, and they let Brigham
Young, the prophet of the church, be the
first governor. Now, the US Congress did
not want to name this after a word from
the Book of Mormon that means beehive.
So, they named it Utah after the local
Ute natives, who this land had been
taken from. Little fun side note here,
the Washington Monument here in
Washington D.C. was built using stones
from every state and territory. And as
this negotiation was going down, the
stone that made it into the Washington
Monument says Deseret, not Utah. It's
got the beehive and a big eye that says
holiness to the Lord, like the most
Mormon symbol you could ever have right
here in the Washington Monument.
So, the Mormons now have a territory
called Utah Territory. It's not a state
yet. President Brigham Young is their
governor and their prophet, and they can
continue to build Zion in peace. But,
the government now sort of has an eye on
them. They send in some federal
employees to like keep an eye on the
Mormons, make sure they don't get too
revolutionary with their theocratic
government and their apocalyptic ideas.
They're once again back on the
government's radar. The government's
like, "They better start behaving like
Americans. They need to quit it with the
whole we're making our own government
and society for the coming of Jesus
thing, or things are going to get
messy."
And now we have to talk about polygamy.
Some of you have been waiting the whole
time to hear me talk about polygamy.
Well, here it goes.
You'll remember from part one that when
Joseph Smith was the leader of the
church, he came out and said that the
Lord had commanded him to take multiple
wives. That this was a [music] part of
the new and everlasting covenant, which
is the law of marriage for Mormons.
Joseph ended up marrying around 40 women
in his lifetime. Some of them very
young. But polygamy wasn't for everyone
at first. Joseph invited a few select
church leaders and people in his circle
to participate in polygamy. And they
continued doing that. Brigham Young also
did this, but in kind of a hush-hush way
for a bit. That is until 1852, a couple
years after Utah territory was created.
Prophet Brigham Young stands at the
pulpit of this very beautiful building
and tells [music] the members of the
church that plural marriage or polygamy
is a divine law from God, a superior way
[music] of life practiced by the
prophets of old. And in this conference,
he cites Joseph Smith's revelation on
marriage, saying that marriage,
including plural marriage or polygamy,
is the only way to be exalted, which is
the Mormon way of saying to become
[music] a god, which is the ultimate
goal in Mormon doctrine. The thinking
was that plural marriage would allow
more worthy women to marry a worthy man
and have the opportunity to be exalted.
Brigham Young went on to marry 56 wives.
He had kids with 16 of them. 57 children
in total. Some of these wives were older
widows that Brigham said he married just
to take care of them.
And some of them were 13 years old.
So now that [music] the prophet had
openly endorsed it, it was public. This
was out. More and more Mormon men
>> [music]
>> began practicing polygamy, taking mostly
younger women as their extra wives. If
you want to look at this graph, pause
the video or go look at my sources cuz
it's [music] pretty interesting. But
let's move on. So unsurprisingly, the
government does not like this. Some
lawmakers in Washington D.C. see
polygamy as the equivalent of slavery,
something that at the time was a fierce
debate in the country, [music] something
that was about to turn into a civil war.
And as the government exerts more and
more control out here in the West,
>> [music]
>> they become less and less comfortable
with the Mormons building their own
theocratic utopia communal society
within the borders of the United States.
And Brigham Young, the governor and
prophet, is not helping the situation,
writing to his followers that the world
is  on the eve of revolution.
Giving speeches [music] to his lawmakers
in Utah Territory, saying that
the government is going to pieces, and
that when the time comes, we shall be
called the kingdom of God. Like the
church is the real government. So, is
this freedom of religion or a brewing
revolution by an apocalyptic religious
group? Add to this that more and more
Americans are hearing about polygamy and
are disgusted. You can see this in this
waterfall of political cartoons.
Brigham Young at home with all of his
wives. All the wives fighting in bed
while the babies cry. An Elders' Happy
Home.
I mean, this stuff is kind of snarky and
fun or whatever, but you also see some
more violent [music] and dehumanizing
depictions. Like Uncle Sam marching with
his sword into Utah, the Mormon vermin
nest. Or lines of women marching into a
skull labeled Utah. The media starts
portraying Mormons as a different race,
less white than other Americans.
But the Mormons don't budge on polygamy.
It's a law of God. Like it's very black
and white. Their prophet has said so.
And in fact, they kind of double down.
Mormon leaders start defending polygamy,
saying that it's a healthier way of
life. Monogamy makes a man dry up and
wither, but a man with lots of wives
looks fresh and young and sprightly.
Why? Because God loves that man. Or
here's another one. Polygamy promotes
life, purity, innocence, vitality, and
health. Monogamy engenders disease,
[music] disappointment, and premature
death. Wow, these are some bold claims.
Eventually, the federal government has
had enough. They see this as an open
rebellion happening within their
borders, and that's when they call in
the troops.
>> [music]
>> War is coming to Utah, and Brigham Young
prepares his men. Calls them back from
their missions, rallies his militia to
fight back against the federal
government that wants to [music] end
their Zion. Now, the Mormon militia,
called the Nauvoo Legion, is not going
to win against the United States Army.
>> [music]
>> So, they resort to kind of insurgent
tactics. They start kind of terrorizing
the supply [music] lines, burning stuff.
They create these cattle stampedes. They
block canyons, anything to slow the
federal troops down. At one point in the
middle of all of this, [music] a group
of the Mormon militia happen upon a
group of settlers who are traveling to
California. They have a standoff, and
eventually the Mormons [music] end up
tricking them into coming out and giving
them their guns, at which point they go
on to massacre almost [music] the entire
group, 120 men, women, and children.
Only a handful of children were spared,
and they were the ones who were too
young to remember what was happening.
But, despite this increased tension,
this event known as the Utah War never
[music]
escalates into a full-blown battle
between the army and the Mormon militia.
Brigham Young ends up [music] backing
down. The Mormons negotiated with the
government, saying that they would allow
the army to come into Utah to keep an
eye on things. Brigham Young also had to
step down, and the government would be
replaced with more non-Mormons. So,
there was a ton of troops in Utah at
this time. It's the 1860s, and the Civil
War breaks out over in the East. And at
that moment, the largest group of
federal troops are stationed in Utah,
keeping an eye on the Mormons.
But, even still, under all of this
scrutiny, people keep coming. The Mormon
communities keep growing. Mormon men
continue to take multiple wives. The
government feels like they're being
ignored. So, back in Washington, D.C.,
lawmakers decide it's time to end the
Mormon project once and for all. And
this time, they're going to do it with
laws.
They pass a series of laws that make
polygamy or anything like it illegal.
The Mormons are now officially breaking
the law, and thousands are rounded up
and put in jail. And crucially, this law
also gives the government power to seize
the church's property, like their funds,
their buildings, including their
precious temples, the most important
[music] place in Mormonism. The
government could argue, and the Supreme
Court would agree, that these temples,
where Mormons get married, were being
used to break the law, because they were
being used to marry men to multiple
women, which was now a felony under the
law. Temples were the final straw for
this community. It represented what
could be the end of their church. So,
the prophet of the time, Wilford
Woodruff, comes out [snorts] and says
that the Lord has showed him a vision of
what will happen if they don't give up
practicing polygamy. He said that their
holy temples would be taken [music]
away. Their men, including their top
leaders, would all be thrown into jail,
and it would be the end of the church. I
mean, he wasn't seeing the future here.
This was already happening, and this was
logically the next step for the church.
So, he commands the members to stop.
Many members of the church listened, and
many totally ignored it and continued to
practice plural marriage for decades.
This includes seven of the top leaders,
called apostles, who continued to
practice polygamy even after the
manifesto. The church did come out a few
years later and said, "No, really, you
have to stop, or we will excommunicate
you." And even still, some disagreed,
leading to a group of them to gather in
a small desert community in Arizona
where they continued to practice
polygamy which they were told was a
celestial law. They eventually became
[music] the Fundamentalist Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints or
FLDS where today they remain where
[music] 30,000 members live in these
insular communities continuing the
practice of polygamy. That is a whole
other rabbit hole for another day.
Mainstream Mormons [music]
did eventually get totally on board and
do not practice polygamy in any kind of
significant way. And Utah was eventually
made [music] a state.
Today, the descendants of those original
pioneers live in Mormon communities
along this corridor that Brigham Young
settled. My wife and I went to school
[music] right here in the heart of it in
this beautiful valley surrounded by
these massive mountains feeling close to
[music] the specific sugar-coated
version of this history that I was
taught. These stories of struggle and
conflict, [music] sacrifice in the name
of your beliefs, bravery in the face of
persecution, a work ethic, [music] and a
discipline, and an obedience that I was
shaped by. [music] A huge part of my
identity and the identity of a lot of
LDS people. But what I've learned
[music] is that that identity is deeply
linked to exploitation and apocalyptic
thinking. Exploitation of Mormon women
and children, the theft of native land,
obedience to a God whose will is
strangely aligned with the incentives
[music]
of men, a belief that the world will end
any day which justifies all of this. A
confirmation [music] that we were the
chosen people, the real Israel,
called of God to prepare the world
[music]
for the end, to gather the tribes before
the savior's return. I still don't fully
understand how I could find [music] such
meaning and beauty in something that I
now find to be so wrong, to be [music]
so damaging.
And yet there's a third and final part
to this story that you have to
understand [music] if you want to
understand the Mormon experience. I'll
eventually be making a third video where
I explain a bizarre pivot that happens
[music] where the Mormons go from being
a rebellious apocalyptic group in the
mountains fighting with the federal
government
>> [music]
>> to embracing it, growing the church into
a global organization who has [music]
used that same beehive cooperative work
ethic to become wealthy and powerful.
Wielding over a hundred billion dollars
[music] in financial assets, all with
the goal of building Zion in preparation
for the end of the world. It's the same
goal that motivated Joseph Smith to
start the church, the same goal that
kept the saints going [music] with
Brigham Young in building out the
mountain west, and it is the same goal
that motivates members of the church
today.
Let me show you this.
That is our freezer, and inside are a
bunch of boxes of Cometeer coffee. We've
kept Cometeer coffee in our freezer for
years, probably since 2022. Love this
stuff.
I also keep some in the fridge
so I can make iced coffee. It's truly
the easiest way to make great coffee. I
can't count the number of times our
guests have asked, "Where can I get
this?" And that's because it's as simple
as
pouring it in here
and boom, within 10 seconds I have a
latte.
This afternoon I'm drinking this slow
motion decaf, which is from Switzerland,
and it's a medium roast that I just love
to drink in the afternoon. You can get
20 bucks off your first order with the
link in my description. This is a
limited edition world mug collection
where you can try all the different
coffees side by side. It's really the
perfect place to start, and I think
you're going to love it.
Okay, back to work.
>> [music]
>> I have applied and I intend on serving a
full-time
2-year mission for the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints. Now, that
might sound ridiculous, that might sound
absurd. Why would you do that for 2
years? Well,
let me tell you why.
I'm born [music] and then blessed.
I learn songs, rhymes, motions, all
teaching me where I came from, why I'm
here, where I'm going. I [singing] am a
[music] child
of God.
I'm 5 years old. [music] I learn to
study a book,
the most perfect book. Book of Mormon
[music]
stories and my teacher [singing] tells
to me
moral
of the
>> [music]
>> land and knights in
>> [singing]
>> ancient history.
>> [music]
>> I learn to follow the prophet.
Follow the prophet,
follow the prophet,
follow the
>> [music]
>> I'm eight and I'm getting baptized. I
can sin now. I can be dirty. Repenting
for those sins is now my [music]
responsibility.
>> Be clean. We live in a world that is
filled with filth and sleaze. You cannot
afford to let that poison touch you.
>> a full member of the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints. They call
us [music] Mormons and I start paying
10% of my income. I don't have any
income, but I'm taught that any money I
[music] get, the first thing I should do
is pay 10% to the Lord. It was hard for
me to give my tithing to the bishop, but
it felt good to be obedient to the Lord.
I'm 12 years old and I receive [music]
the priesthood. My beloved brethren of
the priesthood
>> With this comes authority.
God's authority. Our young people are
the nobility of heaven. I get to pass
the bread and water to the congregation.
Girls don't have the priesthood, but
they're learning other important skills.
I'll marry one of them one day.
If I'm worthy, once a month I get to go
with other teenagers to this ornate
building, the temple.
Such an important building. I dress in
white and get baptized [music] in this
font that sits atop 12 oxen. Not
baptized for myself, but for someone
else, someone who has died, but never
got to hear about the restored gospel.
I'm being baptized as their proxy,
giving them a chance to make it to the
celestial kingdom.
>> [music]
>> As soon as I'm in high school, I begin
waking up every morning at 5:30 to go to
a church educational seminary. All
before the school day actually begins.
Monday nights are family home [music]
evening. Wednesday nights all the youth
get together at the church. Sundays we
meet for 3 hours. We don't work on
Sundays. We don't watch movies. We don't
listen to music. We're not supposed to
buy anything. We [music] do all of that
on Saturday because, as I've been
singing since I was five,
>> [music]
[singing]
>> My weekends are spent volunteering. None
of my friends are doing anything close
to this in their free time. I'm
different.
But I'm not weird. I go to school
dances, I play sports, I'm in the band,
I'm the homecoming prince.
At church we're taught that we need to
be social.
We need to be charismatic and fun. We
are ambassadors of the church. We're
taught that
>> that though we are in the world, we must
not be part of it. We must not be
influenced by those who would call us
peculiar.
>> And my non-Mormon friends wonder why my
family is so close, why we're always so
happy, why we work so hard.
>> [music]
>> I get my first job at Dairy Queen, my
first paycheck. I start paying tithing.
I go to Mormon youth camp during the
summer. We dance and we sing, we play,
we perform, and feel feelings we aren't
sure are ours.
>> [music]
>> I graduate high school.
And instead of joining a frat, I get a
letter. [music]
I open it up and it's an assignment.
I'll be spending 2 years of my life
volunteering on a mission to spread the
gospel.
They're sending [music] me to Tijuana.
2-year mission for the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints. Now, that
might sound ridiculous, that might sound
absurd. Why would you do that for 2
years? Well,
let me tell you why.
Before I leave on my mission, I get
inducted into the [music] highest order
of the priesthood and I go through some
pretty intense rituals in the temple.
Stuff I'm not allowed [music] to talk
about. There's special clothing, special
gestures,
lots of promises, [music] very serious
promises.
Promises of commitment, of loyalty.
Elder John Harris reporting.
Then suddenly I find myself in a small
border town in the desert of northern
Mexico. [music]
2 years.
I spend nearly every waking moment
[music] knocking on doors, talking to
people in a language I'm getting better
at every day, studying the doctrine, and
spreading the most important story of
all, that Joseph Smith [music] restored
God's true church in 1830.
I follow a strict [music] dress code,
even when it's 110° outside.
There's no free time, there's no music,
there's no books or [music] movies, no
vacation, no pay, no girlfriends.
I write letters to my friends [music]
and I get a phone call with my parents
on Christmas and Mother's Day.
All my non-Mormon friends are at college
discovering their academic interests,
their sexuality, their tolerance for
alcohol, while I'm discovering how hard
I can push my body and mind, how good I
can get at Spanish, how compelling I can
make the message [music] sound. Every
day is planned down to the minute,
something I still do today.
The mission requires us to collect
[music] data on how many people I spoke
to, how many lessons I taught, how many
people I asked to be baptized. [music]
I'm trying to baptize as many people as
I can.
Soon I'm leading a group of 20
missionaries, encouraging [music] them,
teaching them, guiding them, training
them, and I'm 20 years old.
I have doubts while I'm in Mexico, but I
bury them very deeply. I put them on the
shelf, and I build my testimony, [music]
my faith, my belief. I need to believe.
I must build his kingdom. We are here to
invite people to understand the laws of
God.
And I discover that I'm good at this.
>> [music]
>> I sit in thousands of homes. I hear
thousands of stories of difficult and
beautiful lives. I meet beautiful
people.
I learn about the violent realities of
borders.
After 2 years of this intensity, I'm a
different person.
I return home, and 10 days later, I'm in
Utah's striking Rocky Mountains on the
Lord's campus, BYU.
I'm surrounded by tens of thousands of
other college-age Mormons. We're not
allowed to have beards or wear tank tops
or drink or have sex outside of
marriage, but [music] that doesn't mean
we don't have fun. At BYU, I meet my
lifelong friends.
The church is subsidizing the majority
of my tuition. I study international
relations and travel the world and no
matter where I go, [music] the church is
there teaching the same lessons, singing
the same songs inside the same looking
buildings as back home.
>> [music]
>> Every 6 months we all travel to Salt
Lake City to gather with tens of
thousands of members from all around the
world and we listen to our church
leaders speak. We believe [music] that
they are prophets, seers and revelators.
This is broadcast to members all around
the world and one of the key messages
throughout all of this training is
family.
>> Family. Family.
Family is the most important thing.
Family is eternal.
I'm 21 and I'm dead-set on finding a
wife. Someone I can start a family with.
It must be another devout Mormon who has
been on this same path.
And I find one.
I'm engaged 10 months after returning
from my mission. Zina I get married in
the temple. We're juniors in college and
soon we're walking for graduation with a
beautiful newborn baby in our arms.
>> [music]
>> At this point, I'm ready. I'm trained.
The church has invested so much in me
and many of us go from here to have
high-paying jobs, to volunteer as
leaders in the church, to be deeply
devoted to running it effectively, to
growing it, to faithfully paying
tithing, all while living productive,
industrious, family-centered lives.
But I don't follow the rest of this
path.
And eventually I find that the answers
are not there for me and I begin to
leave.
>> [music]
>> And since then, I've been trying to
understand it, to understand how the
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints created [music]
this, created me.
A part of that processing has taken
[music] place here on this channel where
I've tried to grasp the context and
history of the church.
And now, in this third and final
chapter, I'm going to show you the last
part of the story. [music] How the
church went from radical, rebel,
polygamist movement who fought with the
US [music] government to this clean-cut,
all-American, increasingly global church
that we know today. [music] How it has
produced such deeply devoted members and
how in the process
they became the richest church on Earth.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Hey. Thanks for watching this long saga.
If you're this far into this
compilation, you're probably a curious
person who likes learning. That's what I
am and a lot of people in this
community. And we have just finished
building a place where we can have a
deeper community experience around
[music] curiosity and understanding. It
is newpress.com. It's a completely free
platform where
>> [music]
>> our community comes to see what we're
working on, to contribute to our
journalism, and to get access to a
deeper version of the work that we do.
[music] My work has always been driven
by curiosity. And more and more, I want
to bring the community and the audience
into that [music] experience. Again,
it's completely free to contribute. You
can head to newpress.com to check it
out. And with that, let's jump into the
next chapter of the story of the Mormon
church.
>> [music]
>> So, we already went into depth about how
the Mormons were driven out of the
United States. They took refuge in the
high desert where they built their own
religious government and kingdom away
from the American government. What would
become Utah, Idaho, and Arizona. They
practiced polygamy. They were rebels.
And eventually the US government cracked
down, almost ended them. And under
intense pressure, they gave in. They
gave up polygamy. A lot of members
didn't want to give this up. They
resisted. Some of them split off
entirely. A prophet had told them that
this was the right thing to do. So, they
left the mainstream church and started a
version of their own.
>> You get a real division then between the
mainstream church and the fundamentalist
polygamist offshoots. And so, that's one
of the real ways in which they're really
trying to distance themselves from that
earlier past. That's Taylor Petrie. He's
a Harvard-trained theologian and an
expert on Mormon history and theology.
He's a practicing member of the church
and between interviews with him and
others and a lot of primary source
research, I'll try to give you my
understanding of what happens next.
>> The church undergoes what scholars call
hyper-Americanization. And it's this
effort to sort of assimilate into the
broader American ideals of the time. The
Mormons go to great lengths in the early
1900s to rebrand, [music] to distance
themselves from their old legacy of
polygamist rebels. I think a sincere
effort to to be a part of the broader
world. And the church sort of looked at
[music] its 19th century in some
respects as a failure precisely because
it had been alienated from the broader
society in which it lived. And at the
same time, I think that it's a way for
the church to [music] demonstrate that
it is a good church and that it does
belong because they have that sort of
chip on their shoulder. [music]
>> And they don't just assimilate, they
actually kind of overcompensate
to become more American than most
Americans. They lean hard into the
American ideal of the nuclear family,
the opposite of polygamy. They encourage
family night for all of their members.
During prohibition, when it was illegal
to sell alcohol here in the United
States, the Mormons jump on board. The
leader of the church starts to strictly
enforce [music] the rules against
alcohol, coffee, tea, and smoking. Tens
of thousands of Mormons go fight in
World War I. They donate money to the
war effort.
>> In 1880s,
they commemorate the 4th of July with a
funeral because they mark it as the
death of actual democracy and liberties
in America due to the anti-polygamy
prosecution. [music] And then in the
early 1900s, they're actually
celebrating America's founding. They're
embracing these patriotic myths. The
general conference addresses are
praising America. They're emphasizing
their patriotic bonafides.
>> Well, in part the church is interested
in its own success, and [music] part of
the way that it can do that is by
imitating their neighbors, but not only
imitating them, trying to do it even
better. This is working. The Mormons are
rebranding. They're becoming more
mainstream. They're like serving as
lawmakers, but very quickly, by like the
1930s,
this assimilation effort creates a
problem, a pretty existential problem
that strikes at the very heart of the
Mormon belief system. Remember the
founder Joseph Smith?
>> [music]
>> Remember how he claimed that he had
translated a new book of scripture from
ancient [music] records, just like the
Bible, but here in the Americas? He
claimed that the Book of Mormon was the
record of a lost American civilization.
It had specific names and battles and
languages and technologies. And because
it was so literal and specific, it made
itself verifiable. It's either true or
it's not, which also made it vulnerable,
vulnerable to science. Archaeology and
geology and linguistics and anthropology
are progressing, and those who look at
Joseph's translations and claims see
them as a fantasy, as an invention of
Smith himself. And soon it wasn't just
non-believers. The dissent was coming
from within.
Brigham Young University, that's where I
went to college. It was a university
that started out as kind of like a
religious school for Mormons. But as a
part of this big Mormon rebrand, they
were trying to make BYU a legit [music]
accredited academic university. The
Harvard of the West is one president of
BYU's [music] exact language of how they
were trying to make BYU legitimate. They
start trying to act like other
universities. They finally get
accreditation. They start hiring people
with PhDs. They give their faculty
research funds. [music] Even some of the
church leaders and official historians
do analyses of the Book of Mormon and
sorrowfully [music]
conclude that the evidence points to
Joseph Smith as having created all this
himself. If you're someone who hasn't
grown up in the church, I don't know how
big of a deal this is going to sound to
you, but it is a huge deal. In the
beginning of the Book of Mormon, which I
have a
copy, actually. Let me grab.
Here in the very introduction, the first
page of the Book of Mormon, Joseph Smith
says that it is the most correct book of
any book on Earth, and that [music] it
is the keystone of our religion.
Keystone, what's a keystone? A keystone
is this, the thing that holds an arch
together. The idea is that if this book
is not a literal record of Jews who came
to America in 600 BC, if Joseph Smith
made it up, then this whole thing falls
apart.
All of the claims fall apart. You must
understand how important this book is to
the modern Mormon church if we're going
to continue the story.
And this keystone idea really explains
what happens [music] next.
>> [music]
>> So here we are in the 1930s on the BYU
campus. And that history, the veracity
of this book, the keystone, is being
questioned and challenged [music] by
science and modern thought. PhDs and
intellectuals diluting and
reinterpreting the core evidence of of
the church's veracity. Now, remember the
church leaders were trying to modernize
and assimilate the Mormon church away
from its polygamous past, but this was
going too far and it was having effect
on the devotion of the members. BYU
students were getting really lax. Their
beliefs were becoming symbolic. They
weren't going to church as much. They
weren't paying their tithing. Up in Salt
Lake City, they are concerned. This
willingness to reinterpret traditional
Mormon beliefs in light of new
scientific and historical learnings.
This stuff, according to the leaders,
would quote strike at the heart of our
LDS teachings. And Joseph Fielding
Smith, one of the leaders who would
become prophet someday, says it most
plainly and accurately, I believe, which
is if such views become dominant in the
church,
>> [music]
>> then we may as well close up shop and
say to the world that Mormonism is a
failure. And I think he's right. This
was existential. If this modernizing of
Mormon doctrine had continued, then the
church could have ended up as a much
less literal faith. It could have still
been a Christian church, but with a much
more symbolic interpretation of Joseph
Smith seeing God, what the Book of
Mormon actually is. That would have been
a much less compelling message. Once you
take away the keystone, the thing falls
apart. They would still have their
central claim that Jesus Christ is the
savior of the world, but every Christian
church has that. That's not special.
Devotion to the message,
>> [music]
>> the thing that drove people across the
ocean and across the plains to sacrifice
their lives and everything they had for
the building [music] of the kingdom on
earth
relied on the veracity of the Book of
Mormon
and the claims [music] that Joseph Smith
actually saw God and that he was chosen
by God
>> [music]
>> to create the one true church and
prepare the world for the second coming.
You see the real legitimate struggle
among Mormons about which direction
they're going to go.
Many of the intellectuals and many of
the lay membership is sort of shifting
in the modernist direction and some of
the leadership as well. And at the same
time you have other leaders who are
nervous about that, who are wanting to
kind of fight to hold on to some of
those earlier values, fundamentalist
conservative Christians. So, the church
leaders needed some kind of stability,
some kind of control. They needed to
re-spark the fervor that the church was
founded on. They needed to fortify their
keystone.
So, one of the top Mormon leaders at the
time head south towards Provo. He's
going to go save the church. Here he is
talking to all of the leaders and
faculty at BYU. He tells them explicitly
that they are to teach the scriptures
and the words of church leaders, not to
promote their private interpretations of
church beliefs. He emphasizes a literal
reading of the Bible and the Book of
Mormon. He emphasizes obedience and
certainty. Telling these professors that
they, quote, are to stand as watchmen
upon the towers of Zion and that they
will be held accountable if they don't.
The message was clear. There is one
truth. It is very clearly articulated by
the leaders who are the prophet seers
and revelators and that they are not to
stray from that. Now, a quick reminder
that the church wasn't like this before.
Joseph Smith founded a church that was
full of debate and contradiction and
interpretation and symbolism. I mean, in
the early days, there were star systems
where God lived. Some of the leaders
said that the Holy Spirit was made up of
physical but intelligent atoms. God
certainly had many wives and [music] men
and women who are sealed by the
priesthood can one day become gods
themselves. And there were tons of gods,
more gods than the particles contained
in a million earths. Women were
experimenting with rituals in the
temple, invoking God's authority,
developing a sacred feminine theology,
and a belief in a heavenly mother, God's
wife. My point here is is that for the
first 100 years, the church was like
full of interpretation. There was not
one centralized articulated belief
system. The leaders would disagree with
each other and they would debate it. And
this worked when they were just a small
band of renegades in the mountains of
Utah, far away from modern [music]
thinking and modern science. But that
flexible mystical approach would not
work in this new era of the church. One
where the church was now in the world,
as we say, integrating with the rest of
society, and now under threat by modern
thinking and scientific scrutiny.
So, this speech at BYU, J. Reuben Clark
is the guy who's giving the speech, and
I'm not going to give you a play-by-play
of everything that happens in modern
Mormon history, but this J. Reuben Clark
moment is so important because it sets a
clear, firm direction
for the church. A movement towards a
more standardized, literal, [music]
controlled theology. One that is not
overly debated by its members.
>> From 1890 to 1930s, there were a number
of potential trajectories the faith
could have taken. J. Reuben Clark's
version won, but that doesn't mean that
the dissenters went away. They just had
to morph over the years, and they've
always been a minority, but they've
always been a loud minority.
>> We'll get back to this central tension
in just a minute, but first, something's
changing about the Mormons' look.
>> [music]
>> So, this rebrand away from polygamy and
towards hyper-American ideals continues,
and it soon affects these beards. After
decades of donning long, wild west
frontier beards, this quote expression
of non-conformity with the rest of the
United States, the newly hyper-American
Mormons did away with the facial hair.
This is David O. McKay, who's one of the
prophets, leaders of the church. He's
the first prophet to go totally
clean-shaven. He gets up in front of the
members, starts to talk to them more
about [music] the way you look to
others, to non-Mormons. He starts
talking about white shirts. Quote, "We
are not so poor that we can't afford
clean white shirts." White shirts. David
O. McKay is a fashionable guy. He's got
a great haircut. He's [music]
clean-shaven. So, the long Brigham Young
beards are banished by the middle of the
1900s. And this is further codified at
BYU. BYU's kind of like the cultural
epicenter of the Mormon church. And they
implement these grooming standards, the
honor code, which says [music] you can't
have beards. Church are kind of adopting
these new fashion statements in these
years and start to look like the modern
businessman during the middle of the
20th century. These identities, these
practices, these kind of cultural tropes
of what the good American would look
like. And that really defines the course
of the 20th century as the church is
adapting to this new environment. And
this is why I looked like this for many
years. I can't convey to you how big of
a deal these grooming standards were in
my entire life up into my early
adulthood. When you are a teenager in
the church, you are given a little book
that is effectively the manual on how
you are to behave and dress [music] and
look. There's a whole section about
grooming. Show respect for the Lord and
yourself by dressing appropriately for
church meetings and activities. Now,
this was a whole different thing if you
were a teenage girl in the church. Your
version of the book focused a lot on
what you wear, modesty. Shorts and
skirts below the knees, no sleeveless
tops. One of the early editions of this
book [music] tell girls that their
clothes should be comfortable and
attractive without calling attention to
a person's body. Strapless dresses and
spaghetti straps are not acceptable
either on sundresses or evening dresses.
Few girls or women ever look well in
backless and strapless dresses. Such
styles often make the figure look
ungainly,
large, and show the bony structures of
the body. And you girls are untrue to
yourselves if you encourage or allow
this to happen. The way you dress or the
way you act makes these guys think that
you're interested in something different
than you really are.
>> So yeah, you start to see a lot of
control and emphasis put on how you
look. From a young age I was ironing
white shirts and tying ties very often.
And we were told explicitly that this
wasn't just about showing respect for
the Lord, but it was also about sending
a message to other people, specifically
non-Mormons. This is from one of the
leaders in 2008, quote, "Our outward
appearance and behavior [music] give a
message. What message are we sending?
Does it reflect that we are children of
God?" Kind of open-ended, but you get
the point. Now, this was my one quiet
rebellion as a Mormon teen, my too long,
shaggy, blond hair, which was always too
long to meet the standard and was
quickly done away with when I was called
to serve a mission in Mexico and had to
abide by much stricter standards that
were not optional.
That kind of corporate [music]
representation that becomes really an
important part of the way the Latter-day
Saints are presenting themselves and is
ultimately going to trickle down to the
rest of the membership and especially
the missionaries too, who are really
going to adopt this costume as the brand
of what Mormons look like.
>> I mean, the church was almost squashed
by a negative perception of Mormons as
polygamists. And so it's like built into
the DNA of the organization
to have a good public perception. We'll
see more of that in a sec.
>> [music]
>> Anyway, speaking of well-groomed
missionaries, look at this graph of the
number of Mormon missionaries going out
into the field in like the middle of the
century. This is right after World War
II. These are like 19-year-old guys,
some women, and they are assigned to
some area in the world for around 2
years. They pay their own way, they're
volunteers, and during this time they
knock on doors and they try to get
people to join the church, and it's
totally working. I mean, look at the
growth of church members into the '50s
and '60s, in large part because of this
missionary effort.
>> The church is really successful in
growing in Central America, in Europe,
in the Pacific Islands, in Australia in
the first couple of decades after World
War II, in part because of its
Americanness and in part because of its
clean-cut symbolism of American values
and especially anti-communist values in
these years.
>> Soon I would be one of these guys doing
the Lord's work in Tijuana. So, at this
point, the Mormon church is really
successful. [music]
Their industrious work ethic has been
redirected from building Zion in the
mountains to building Zion within the
American system and around the world,
and the message is resonating and
members are joining from all over the
world, and they come in with different
cultural backgrounds into this church
that was started in upstate New York.
And here we are back to this very
existential debate that we saw in the
'30s with J. Reuben Clark and the
intellectuals at BYU. Well, it was sort
of happening again, not with PhDs, but
with like people in Samoa, in France,
and Japan, who all came from very
different cultural backgrounds and were
now getting baptized into this [music]
very American church. And this is a
problem because it starts to fracture
the message, the doctrine, the belief
system [music] as it blends with all of
these local traditions. The leaders back
in Salt Lake didn't have control over
exactly what they were teaching in every
branch and church congregation around
the world. So, the leaders set about
once again trying to unify the church
under one message so that a lesson being
taught in Peru is the exact same [music]
as the one being taught in Provo that
week. Otherwise, you'll start to get
spin-off beliefs. They needed
consistency everywhere.
>> [music]
>> So, the top leaders of the church get a
committee together and they spend a good
part of the 60s rewriting everything.
All the manuals, all the official church
doctrine and policies and procedures
into super clear language. And once they
started, they kept going. They decided
they wanted to reshape not just the
teaching manuals, but the entire
organization into a hierarchy that
starts with the prophets and apostles at
the very top in Salt Lake who would
influence and control everything that
happened below it. For the first time,
all teacher development in the church
will be correlated under the direction
of the priesthood. The church will
supersede all other teacher training
programs. The bishop in every
congregation anywhere on earth would get
a handbook that lays out the official
policies and procedures in black and
white language. [music]
All local variations of beliefs and ways
of doing things would be replaced with
fresh standardized manuals and direction
[music] from the top with specific
verbiage and words and phrases on how to
talk about Joseph Smith's revelations
and how to teach the Book of Mormon, how
to teach the Bible, what to say and what
not to say. It would all need to be
developed by these men in Salt Lake who
were grappling with this tension of
trying to modernize and mainstream their
church while also making sure that the
very bold set of beliefs doesn't get
watered down because the devotion of the
members relied on them buying into that
central message, one that was under
threat [music] by different cultures or
modern ways of thinking. And the answer
to this big challenge was to centralize,
to control, to bring everything under
>> [music]
>> the priesthood in Salt Lake. The
priesthood being the authority that God
gave to Joseph Smith that was given to
all white men at the time and then later
to every man in 1978. So, that
correlation movement is a sort of
doctrinal consolidation, a pretty
interesting technocratic revolution of
reorganizing the entire church from top
to bottom. The women's organization,
called the Relief Society,
had a long history of being autonomous,
being sort of its own subculture within
Mormonism. And they had a lot of control
over what they taught, how they taught
it. But under correlation, the
priesthood or the male body of the
leadership really kind of takes control
of all of that. The women's [music]
curriculum really changes during these
years. The Relief Society, the women's
organization, is really involved in
social outreach, in food drives, and
providing social services was its kind
of main mission. But in the post-World
War II era, it shifts to teaching
[music] women how to be wives and
mothers as its primary way of
understanding itself. They shut down the
Relief Society's magazine and all other
magazines [music] and replaced them with
three official approved magazines. One
for adults, one for youth, and one for
kids. And yes, that continued. I grew up
with these magazines on the coffee table
in my house. A coffee table that never
saw a cup of coffee. And if you're
wondering, like, what version of the
Mormon doctrine and history won out in
all of this, it's the one that J. Reuben
Clark had preached [music] to BYU
faculty in the '30s. One that
simultaneously distanced itself from the
radical, mystical, [music]
theological ideas of the early church,
while simultaneously embracing and
codifying and defining some of the very
unique beliefs. A literal version of the
church's [music] mission. It was still
totally centered on Jesus Christ. It was
the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints. That's the official name [music]
of the church. But in these manuals,
Jesus's atoning sacrifice was to be
accessed exclusively through this system
of [music]
rituals, and authority, and orderly
procedure that was exclusively
administered by the LDS Church. The
conservative [music] church leaders
themselves are incredibly effective at
consolidating their power and kind of
shutting [music] out the other voices
and the other perspectives. And this
correlation moment
>> [music]
>> represents kind of the end of
progressive theological thinking and
debate and disagreement [music]
and gray area in the church.
>> That's really kind of the time when
church leaders say, "This is really
[music] bad for us. If we're so publicly
disagreeing with one another, it's
undermining the broader faith and our
authority." And so, church leaders kind
of
>> [music]
>> tacitly all agree that they're not going
to publicly criticize one another. All
the general authorities of the unity the
like of which we've never experienced in
my
lifetime, unified, working as one voice.
Now, what's surreal is that I didn't
know any of this when I was growing up,
kind of by design. The church I grew up
in and the one that still exists today
was so deeply standardized around these
manuals and procedures and beliefs that
came from one source, the 15 men at the
top, who were able to spread this
version of the belief and the history
through a huge network of distribution.
There were bookstores where you can buy
all the approved manuals and teachings.
There were stickers and highlighters and
book bags and activities. Every Mormon
church was identical, the same chairs
and floors and layouts and woodworks.
It's actually a pretty efficient design.
I was in one recently for a funeral and
I was like, "Man, this is a great
design." It always came with a really
nice gym. Every church had these same
scratchy wall protectors that as a kid
feel like sharp spikes. But yeah, it was
the same everywhere. We sang the same
songs. We used the same insider lexicon.
The same lessons are being taught in
every Mormon church around the globe on
the same day. Like when you're traveling
to a foreign country and you're far away
from home in the mountains of Guatemala
and you go to a Mormon church and you
sit down and hear the same songs and the
same lessons, boy does that make you
feel like you are a part of a global
community. It is a sense of belonging
that you can't really get anywhere else.
But this is just the beginning. The
church made movies, like high quality
movies that brought a lot of these
approved beliefs to life. The official
version of Joseph Smith's story was
represented to me so clearly in these
high quality films. Joseph
This is my [music] beloved son.
The story of the Book of Mormon, again
the keystone of the religion, was
brought to life with ambitious film
production.
>> [music]
>> That movie's called The Testaments. I
watched that probably 500 times on my
mission in Spanish. I like have most of
it memorized in Spanish.
>> [music]
>> Okay, then there was a whole genre of
Mormon videos that modeled how we,
especially as like youth, were to
behave. How we're supposed to apply
these approved teachings in a modern
world.
>> [music]
[singing]
>> They made custom music about the Mormon
doctrine that we would listen to and it
was actually kind of good. Was it good?
I don't know. There were original
musicals.
>> [music]
>> No, not that musical. This one.
>> [music and singing]
>> There were comedy movies about going on
missions. There was jewelry to remind us
to choose the right. And if that wasn't
enough, these centralized messages and
values were reinforced in pithy posters.
Posters like this.
>> [music]
>> A lot of us hung these on our wall. We
looked at them every day, reminding us
of the importance of cleaning our sin,
to dress modestly, to prepare to go to
the temple, the physical truth of the
gold plates, the aspiration to go on a
mission, and most plainly of all, the
call to just believe in this, the
keystone of the religion, is this guy's
story and his claims.
As a teenager, you get this special
blessing from a seasoned priesthood
holder, a patriarch. He interviews you,
and then he puts his hands on your head,
and he kind of riffs. The spirit speaks
to him to [music] foresee your future.
He tells you about how you will go on to
be a faithful member of the church, get
married in the temple, go on a mission,
serve in the church. For me, he threw in
a few vague things that I like got
excited about and was like, "Oh, I
wonder what this means." But I believed
it was like a fortune, like what was
going to happen in my future. So, then
his wife transcribed it, prints it out,
you laminate it, and you make multiple
copies, and you carry it around with
you. And you like read it often. [music]
It's called a patriarchal blessing. And
you watch as your life unfolds and
hopefully is as blessed as your
patriarchal blessing says it will be.
Man, I hadn't thought about that for
years until I started doing this story,
and I was like,
"That felt so normal." It felt so
normal. It doesn't feel like voodoo
magic, doesn't feel like fortune
telling. It feels awesome. It feels like
I have access to a guy with the
priesthood who is going to see my future
and give me guidance about my future.
Like, that's an amazing thing if you
believe that. And when you don't,
woah. And then, perhaps most impactful
of all in this information ecosystem is
this.
>> [music and singing]
>> This is general conference. Every 6
months, so twice a year, tens of
thousands of Mormons gather in Salt Lake
in this big conference center and they
sit for a total of 10 hours over the
course of the weekend to listen to their
prophets and leaders speak to them. We
also get to hear our famous choir sing,
which is like an incredibly powerful
experience when you're sitting in this
room.
>> [music]
>> And this conference is broadcast to the
entire world thanks to the church's
vast, sophisticated broadcasting
abilities. Now, if you've never
experienced being surrounded by 21,000
believers
who believe
down to the word
kind of exactly what you do.
It's a
dare I say beautiful experience of
belonging and of specialness. I don't
know, I get a weird nostalgia when I
look at general conference stuff and
remember sitting in that big, [music]
beautiful room listening to that choir
because you feel so lucky. Like
something big is happening.
>> [music]
>> The end of the world is coming
and you are lucky enough to be sitting
watching prophets who are called of God
and given the authority to prepare the
world for the second coming of Jesus
Christ and you are one of the lucky ones
who's there. It's really powerful. The
church [music] is growing rapidly as our
missionary force introduces the gospel
in all parts of the world.
>> kind of see how this works? This
organization controlling the message
from Salt Lake and really efficiently
and powerfully spreading that message to
the members. It creates unity through
authority and it works. A reminder that
most of the people who run the church
are not paid. They do it as a volunteer.
They have normal jobs and then they go
run the church in their off time. And
they're not just like showing up and
giving a sermon. They are running a
company full of tons of paperwork. The
church is full of so much paperwork and
data. We collect data on member
attendance, and there's meeting notes,
and there's forms and records and
databases of every aspect of the church.
As a missionary, which you are paying to
be out there as a missionary, you are
like an administrative
like foot soldier for the church. You're
filling out forms and turning in reports
and updates. You're looking at
spreadsheets and charts of the number of
lessons you taught and the number of
baptisms you did that month. There are
maps which delineate the whole world
into what priesthood authority is over
what region. Here I am with a binder of
every member that is registered within
the geographic area of the town of
Mexicali, Mexico, and I'm performing an
audit to help update the church records.
This is something I did on my mission.
And we use this as an excuse to teach
people as well.
But, in the process we were getting the
church's books in order. And I kind of
thrived in this. It was the first time
in my life that I thrived at anything. I
got really bad grades in school. I kind
of thought I was not going to be good at
anything. Then I get out on a mission,
and I'm really good at it, and I'm
learning all these skills, and I'm a
leader, and it's like
man, that drove a lot of devotion for me
during that time. It felt good to be
good at something.
And it was God's mission. I've been
looking through these journals. I have
all these journals of every single day
of my mission documented. I'm a
documenter. Always have been. I mean, I
I have so much of this. This is like the
very beginning here, actually.
This was the book that was the clearest
reference for every single doctrine and
belief of the church in alphabetical
order with scriptural footnotes, plain
language, everything from who God is to
what fornication is to gambling for
ordination, family home evening, eternal
life, church disciplinary councils,
[music] scary. There's so much stuff in
here.
We [music] used to do this thing on our
mission where we would have Yodo y
Cloro. It was like bleach and food dye
and we would do this thing where we
would put the food dye in water and it
would like stain the water and we'd say,
"This is what it looks like when you
sin." And then we would take out the
Cloro, the chlorine, the bleach and we
would take a little teaspoon of it and
drop it into the cup
>> [music]
>> and the water would go clean.
And then we would turn to them and say,
"That is baptism. Will you get
baptized?" And we had all these
techniques to challenge someone to be
baptized.
And yeah, that that was the whole point,
just to baptize [music] people. I
baptized a lot of people in the ocean,
which felt [clears throat] cool.
When I talk to people who were never in
this, it's so easy for them to look
[music] at us, those who like when we
were in the church, as just brainwashed,
like we're just [music] doing what we're
told. And yes, in seeing this system of
information being funneled into a very,
very specific and black and white
repetition of the same story, I I see
that. I see that. That makes sense. And
yet, when you're in it, it also feels
very meaningful and all the corporate
repetition, whatever, it feels worth it
because
you really believe that you are
preparing the world, that you are chosen
to do this, that you are a part of a
bigger thing
and that motivates you to volunteer and
to sacrifice and it also drives a lot of
deep relationships and a lot of meaning
in your life. And as much as I am very
critical of this and the way that it was
done to me and to others, I can't say
that it isn't meaningful. I can't say
that it isn't like a really powerful way
to live. Anyway, I'm off topic here cuz
this is also personal for me, but let's
get back to this history and why the
church got so rich. And that has to do
with what happens in the 1970s.
>> [music]
[music]
>> First off, the Mormons never stopped
with their campaign to rebrand away from
polygamy and their kind of weird
beliefs. They continue doing this in the
70s.
>> Every few decades, you got church
leaders that will commission a report
from outside experts and basically
asking, "How can we present [music]
better to the world?" One of the biggest
examples of this is in the early 1970s,
they hire a consulting firm to figure
out how to improve our image. And that
consulting firm says, "Hey, you need to
downplay doctrines and you need to
highlight the family." [music] And
that's when the church starts doing all
those commercials during the 1970s of
the family.
>> Take an interest in your family.
>> It's about time and they have inserts
into Reader's Digest and they're able to
emphasize, "This is how we prove that
we're safe and American as we emphasize
the nuclear family." It's really the
1970s when the church makes that the
message.
>> The important lessons in life are
learned at home
>> [music]
>> from the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints.
I mean these commercials, which are
highly nostalgic for me, are great
messages, [music]
like universal messages. There's no
weird beliefs about God living on a star
or like you getting your own planet.
It's [music] just straight-up family
values. Families grow closer one
conversation at a time. And yes, it's
totally [music] PR, but it's also real
from the inside. Like Mormons live
[music] these values. Very, very
family-focused. Now, there's some
caveats to that and then I have some
critiques, but that's like I will talk
about that with other ex-Mormons. It's
not really like worth going into here.
This rebranding campaign continues
[music]
into the modern day. You may have seen
the I'm a Mormon campaign. And I'm a
Mormon.
>> And I'm a Mormon. I'm a Mormon. And I'm
a Mormon. [music]
And I think all of these efforts, 100
years of of like rebranding Mormons from
[music] like
rebel polygamist to
mainstream good family value Americans
really [music] worked. I talked to a lot
of people who were like, "Man, Mormons,
like they are I know they have weird
beliefs, I know they have secret
underwear,
>> [music]
>> they're just so nice and like
family-centered." There's like a paradox
in that that like no one can [music]
quite square, and I think it's this.
We used to be told often that we live in
the world, but we are not of the world,
[music] meaning we have to play by the
rules, we play in the system, and we do
it well. We do it better than everyone
else.
But we don't adopt the beliefs [music]
of the world. I mean, they have an army
of professionals working on how to shape
and craft the image, and they put in
lots [music] of time and resources and
attention into it. So, how the church is
presenting itself through its media
empire is often [music] a key into how
the church wants itself to be viewed.
Now, once the church is fully
centralized around this messaging
information ecosystem, the other thing
that they must do is continue to
demonize intellectuals and anyone who is
questioning the line of the church.
They've already done this quite a bit,
but they continue to do it in the '70s
and '80s. Boyd K. Packer is one of the
leaders who I grew up listening to, who
was like the staunchest
anti-intellectual, anti-feminist person
you could ever imagine.
He talked about the dangers that come
from so-called scholars and
intellectuals, and they developed this
phrase that becomes embedded in my
psychology. I don't even know from
where, but it's there, and that phrase
is
>> anti-Mormon literature.
>> Anti-Mormon literature.
>> Anti-Mormon literature. This is a scary
thing, or at least it was when I was you
know, 16 and 23. And you're not really
sure what anti-Mormon literature is, but
you know it when you see it. It is
anything that contradicts the official
line of the church. A Reddit post that
wants to like open up, you know, Joseph
Smith's many wives and the fact that one
of them was a child, that's anti-Mormon
literature. That New York Times article
that I showed you at the beginning that
debunks Joseph Smith translations, I had
never seen that until I started
reporting the story. In addition to
getting information from the top, we are
also trained and taught to keep
information out.
>> read the anti-Mormon materials. None of
it is worth casting an eye upon.
Theological pornography. Now, that's
changing a little bit in the church in
the modern day, I hear, like there's
there's more openness, but my entire
childhood in the church in the '90s and
the 2000s, before people started to
leave in mass, there was very little
tolerance and in fact a active
demonization of anti-Mormon literature.
>> [music]
>> In fact, any leader or historian who was
behind any of this work would be
sidelined, kicked out of leadership, or
even excommunicated from the church for
publishing histories or anything that
contradicted the church's official line.
This continued in my era with this woman
Kate Kelly who was a fervent believer in
the church and was like, "Hey, let's
like grow up and give women the
priesthood." And she fought for that and
they excommunicated her. Like, this is
not a place for debate. But this isn't
all. It's not just information and
history being controlled by people in
Salt Lake. It's also about temples.
>> [music]
>> Temples are these very important
buildings. They're beautiful buildings.
They're sacred buildings for Mormons.
It's where they do the most important
rituals that you need to go to heaven.
Well, not just heaven, but the highest
tier in heaven. To get up here to this
highest tier, you also have to get
married in a temple. I got married in
one of these temples here in Portland,
which is right next to the freeway,
which you will see, again, a
brand-minded Mormon church puts their
temples in very visible places so that
people ask questions. Smart move.
Washington, D.C., San Diego. I was
literally taking a boat through the
Panama Canal the other week, and I'm
flying my drone, and I look over, and
what's right there on the crossroads of
the two oceans?
A Mormon temple. Anyway, you're not
allowed to go inside of these temples,
these most sacred places that you must
go into to go to heaven, unless you have
one of these. This is a tiny card with a
barcode on it. It's called a temple
recommend. You have to get one of these
from your local priesthood leader, like
your bishop. And to get it, you have to
go to his office and sit down, and he
asks you 15 questions. So, just imagine
this, you're sitting in a room alone
with this man who you trust. He's like a
part of your community. He's like your
authority. And he asks me point-blank,
"Do you have a testimony of the
restoration of the gospel of Jesus
Christ?" Meaning that Joseph Smith
[music] restored the one true church.
"Do you sustain the president of the
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints [music] as the prophet, seer, and
revelator, and the only person on the
earth authorized to exercise all
priesthood [music] keys?" Keys are like
the authority to administer the church.
So, now they're asking you point-blank,
"Do you think that the prophet is the
only person on earth who has the
authority to do God's work?" And then it
says, "Do you follow the teachings of
the church in your private and public
behavior? Do you support any teaching,
practice, or doctrine contrary to the
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints? Do you keep the Sabbath day
holy? Do you strive to be honest? Are
you a full tithe payer?" That's a big
one. You can't go in the temple unless
you pay. "Do you keep the [music]
covenants that you made in the temple,
like wearing the garments, the
undergarments that you're supposed to
wear. Are there serious sins in your
life that need to be resolved with a
priesthood authority? And all of this
leads to the final question, which is,
are you worthy?
And all of these questions, these really
point-blank, black and white questions
of do you obey the teachings of the
church? Do you pay the tithing? Do you
believe in the restoration? Are meant to
evaluate whether or not you're worthy.
If you answer correctly to these 15
questions, you get a temple recommend.
If you don't, if you do not, then you do
not get a temple recommend. You cannot
go to the temple, even if your sister is
getting married or your child is getting
married. If you have sinned, you've done
some sexual misdeed, you will get your
temple recommend taken away from you.
And then you can't go in the temple, and
instead you go on a [music] process of
repentance where you don't take the
bread and water on Sunday. And your
whole community sees you, and you feel
shame, and you feel embarrassment, and
you feel hopefully sorrow and and
repentance for your sin. And with time,
the bishop then says, "Okay, you're
worthy again. You've repented." I got my
temple recommend taken away once, and it
was horrific. It was a bad, bad 6 weeks.
I felt horrible. I felt shame, and I was
supposed to be getting married in the
temple. It was coming up. My marriage
date was coming up, and I didn't have my
temple recommend. And in the same way
that it feels so good to be in it and
surrounded by believers and worthy, it
feels so bad to be shamed from it, and
to be seen as dirty for going a little
too far with your girlfriend or
something. So, this is the other piece
of it. Yes, it's about teachings and
manuals and, you know, structures, but
it is also about affirming your loyalty
to the doctrine, to the organization, to
the people in charge. And there are
major consequences socially and
psychologically if you don't.
So, let's talk about money now, because
you now have a picture of what it's like
to be in the Mormon church, the devotion
and the sense of loyalty that you
experience, the sense of belonging. And
you now have a sense of to go in the
temple, which you need to do to be
sealed to your family and to [music] go
to heaven, the top part of heaven, you
have to pay 10% of your income. And at
the end of the year, you do this thing
called tithing settlement, [music]
where you go to that same office, to
that same bishop, gives you a piece of
paper that's like, "Here's all the
tithing you said you paid. Is it a full
tithe?
>> [music]
>> Have you actually paid your full
tithing?"
And you say, you look the guy in the eye
and you're like, "Yes, I did." And you
sign it. And you [music]
like it tithing is so important. What
are they doing with the money? Is the
question. And the answer is, well,
they're a church, they're probably
building the church and they're probably
doing humanitarian work. The Mormons are
always doing humanitarian work, right?
Yes. And they're not paying taxes on any
of that because they're a church, a
charity. But by the 1970s, they start
using the money for something fairly
unique.
>> [music]
>> There are a number of church leaders who
are being drawn from the corporate world
to kind of take their expertise. And so,
you get high-powered CEOs and others who
were sort of drafted into church
leadership to take it in this new
direction. One leader in particular, N.
Eldon Tanner, was a business powerhouse
from Canada. He was like an oil tycoon,
super good at business, super loyal to
the church. I actually grew up with N.
Eldon Tanner's descendants, like his
great-grandkids were like my closest
friends as a kid. I heard a lot about
this guy. He was a legend because he
came in with all of his business skills
and pointed them at the church and said,
"We are going to turn this into a an
efficient organization that makes money
instead of just spends all the tithing
we get." He cut costs, he creates all
this financial discipline, and he He to
envision a church that invests that
money into stocks and bonds and real
estate. And they start doing this. And
he standardized a church finances, said,
"Okay, tithing's only going to go to
this, and then we're going to take an
amount of our profits from that. We're
going to hire financial professionals in
Wall Street, and they're going to
control our trust fund to be able to
grow, and we're only going to spend X
percentage [music] of our money a year
so that we can always have the rainy day
fund." So, that slowly grows, and those
funds, just due to the financial
interest and compounded interest, by the
Reagan era of the 1980s and the
neoliberalism of the 1990s, those
investments explode, and they make the
church massively financially wealthy.
So, this could be an entire video. The
financial growth of the LDS Church from
the '70s to today is a mind-blowing
thing. I'll give you the highlights. The
first highlight is look at this map. I
have to say it at some point in the
video, right? This is all of the
agriculture and commercial and
hospitality and industrial and special
purpose and retail land that is owned by
the Mormon Church. There's huge ranches
and farms. But, you know what else
they're investing in? Me. People like
me. I went to BYU, which, by the time I
went there, was like a good university.
And 70% of my tuition was subsidized by
the church. And this is an investment
because we go to BYU, we graduate with
these degrees from increasingly
prestigious programs, like the business
or the accounting program. And by then,
we are in it. We've been through the
whole pipeline, all the training, the
mission, all of the standardized
teaching over and over and over again,
the same message. We're devoted, and we
will be loyal tithe payers for the rest
of our lives. Well, not all of us.
Sorry. [music] I was not a good
investment for the church, but a lot of
people graduate from BYU, go on to make
a ton of money, and give a lot of that
to the church. The business school at
BYU, by the way, is the Marriott School
of Business. Yes, that Marriott. He's
Mormon. And it's housed in a building
that is named after Enos A. Wall and
Tanner. These are the business titans
[music] that established the church not
just as like a corporate entity in its
hierarchy and its look, but also in its
finances and its investment strategies,
in its corporate structure, in its
legal, in its like it They got so
sophisticated. And look what happens. It
pays off. [music] Even today, many of
the senior church leadership, if not at
the 12, at the level of the 70, are
drawn from the ranks of very
high-powered lawyers and corporate types
who can manage the church's vast
resources efficiently. They're often not
chosen for their theological
or doctrinal understanding or even their
great public speaking skills. They're
often chosen because they happen to be
really good at their jobs of kind of
managing large organizations.
>> Like in the last decade, it's estimated
that their wealth has grown a hundred
billion dollars. A hundred billion
dollars. And over 200 billion dollars of
that is just pure hard cash that is in
like stocks and bonds. Walmart doesn't
have that much money on hand. And they
are considered the richest religious
organization in the world if you didn't
count like the Catholic Church, which
isn't one organization. The church is
kind of more centralized, and so on this
Wikipedia article, that's why they put
them at the top. Anyway, they're
incredibly rich for being such a small
church. How do they spend their money?
Well, we have some decent data on this.
Right here at the top, they spend some
of their money on humanitarian aid.
Doing projects around the world, they
spend even more on aid that they give to
their members. Like for members in need,
food assistance, things like that. Then
they spend about a billion dollars on
church education. So much of what we
talked about in this video is this
budget. It is the curriculum. It is the
teaching. It is BYU. Good a good
This is the stuff that informed my
worldview.
>> [music]
>> And then there's this big chunk that is
just operating the church, the
buildings. There are some paid people,
they have to pay them. [music] But look
at this. The vast majority of the money
they spend is on reinvesting to grow
their vast wealth. That's like 65% of
all of their expenditures is just
reinvesting. I did not know this growing
up and I don't think many did. I don't
know, I thought my money was like going
to grow the church, build temples and
you know, humanitarian stuff. I was just
like, you know, like or that they do
humanitarian projects. They are, but
it's just not that much. And listen,
that's actually really rational. The
church never said that their mission was
to be humanitarian. Their mission is to
fulfill the mandate given to Joseph
Smith, which is to prepare the world for
the second coming of Jesus Christ by
spreading the good news of the
restoration and giving people the
opportunity, dead and alive, to get
baptized and do all the rituals. That is
their mission.
And they believe that they need a giant
rainy day fund to do that and I don't
totally know why. Like what their what
their plan is, but boy, they they've got
a lot of money. Now, a few years ago,
one of the employees of the investment
firm for the church was like
uncomfortable with this. You know, he's
like a member of the church, believer,
and he like comes out and he's like,
"This is weird that the church has so
much money." Specifically, he alleged
that there was like a hundred billion
dollars that was supposed to go to some
charitable thing and it wasn't. That
ended up not really going anywhere.
There wasn't any like fallout there. But
it did draw attention to all of this.
And the SEC did end up finding the
church, discovering that they were using
a bunch of shell companies all around
the country to hide how much money they
had because they didn't want anyone to
know that they were sitting on so much
cash. And they paid a fine and since
2019, they have been complying with the
right way to file their taxes and pay
taxes on the stuff that they have to.
So, what do the members of the church
think about their tithing being used to
run a hedge fund. And the answer is
we'll never know because there isn't a
culture of debate and dissent. But I can
tell you by proxy is if I were a member
of the church, I [music] would actually
think this is a great thing. I would be
like this is proof that the Lord wants
us to succeed. [music] He has blessed us
with amazing financial returns
and this is proof and my church is
awesome and look, we [music] are living
the dream and fulfilling the prophecy.
That's what I would feel and I'm sure a
lot of people do. And then of course
there's non-Mormons who are
uncomfortable with this idea of a
tax-free organization being able to just
be a giant investment firm. Curious what
you all think. I'm slightly biased in
all this. Anyway, the point is it drew a
lot of attention to this very
image-minded church who since then has
started investing a lot in humanitarian,
way more than they were before [music]
and we can assume that that is a
reaction to the scrutiny.
>> [music]
>> So, here we are in modern day. The
Mormon church has seen a lot of people
leaving like I did. [music] I mean this
is happening to almost every religious
organization at least in the west. The
[music] church is growing rapidly in
places like South America and Africa as
the missionary [music] effort continues.
And though I haven't been in the church
for a few years, I've seen that the
newest leader has softened some of
[music] the culture that I grew up with.
There's a bit of a reversal of what we
saw in the 50s and 60s where [music] the
church, which is now more international
than ever, is inviting more local
variations on how Mormonism is practiced
around the world. [music] They've also
started publishing more transparent
versions of history instead of the
sugar-coated stuff that I grew up with.
So there is some updating and flexing
[music] to the times on a few small
things. But the doctrine itself, the
keystone of the religion, the stuff
we've talked about hasn't changed. It's
still a very high commitment, high
control [music]
religion with very bold doctrinal
beliefs. The church's priesthood
authority, which can only be held by
men, being central to their existential
story of the world and its imminent end.
>> [music]
>> I'll end by giving you a final
reflection here, which [music] is I left
this organization or started leaving it
about 10 years ago. And I was able to
have the courage [music] to do it
because it was the first time that I was
out of the pipeline, the pipeline of of
information [music] and social and
psychological ramifications for leaving.
I I'd left BYU [music] and I was finally
ready to to start to question it. And
even still, it was really hard. [music]
And still is. I have spent that decade
rewriting my [music]
understanding of worthiness
and value and meaning because I was
given [music] a version of it that was
very, very, very strongly communicated
through a lot of repetition [music] and
from very authoritative people. I have
spent the decade rewriting my need to
[music]
act as an ambassador for a misunderstood
organization, to be liked [music] by
people. That's deep in me because it's
been trained into me from a very young
age. And most complicated of all, I have
been [music] trying to untangle my
feelings of the reality of the harm that
[music] was done to my mind from the
fact that the church is in me. It is me.
[music]
My work ethic, my industriousness,
my curiosity, my ability to [music]
speak Spanish, my family-focused
nature and kindness is attributable to
the church. [music] That's a sort of
impossible contradiction as I've talked
about before and I don't think I'll ever
really sort of reconcile that. But if
there's one thing I feel really clear
about and more clear than ever after
[music] having been deep in this story,
the real version of this story, it's
that all of this was made possible
because of one thing and that thing is
control. [music]
Control of the story of my life by
someone else and not just any part of my
life, the most intimate and personal
parts of my life that were controlled by
the messaging of a group of men in Salt
Lake City. [music] And a group of men
that I believed in willingly or or
seemingly willingly. And men who I think
earnestly believe that this is their
calling. That God wants them to do this,
to keep me on the straight and narrow.
This is what it [music] demanded. The
correlated centralized church is such a
powerful mechanism for repetition,
clarity, certainty. It burrows its way
into you in a way that I
can't really describe. [music] That did
a number on my mind
and the minds of of of a lot of us who
have had the courage to take the story
back.
To redefine
our worthiness and our value
>> [music]
>> away from
the story uh that we were told. To
define that worthiness based on what is
inside of us and not on loyalty and
compliance [music] with the rules of a
corporate organization
that made us believe
that it had the authority to tell us who
we are.
>> [music]
>> Here's what genuinely surprised me when
I started drinking Communitarian like
three or 4 years ago.
You can actually taste where the coffee
comes from. Like their Ethiopian roast
tastes like jasmine and stone fruit. The
Colombia roast tastes like caramel and
red apple. These robust flavors don't
survive when [music] they're just vacuum
sealed into pods or sitting on grocery
shelves for months like other types of
coffee. Only Cometeer delivers flavors
like this straight to your kitchen. And
this box, the world mug collection box,
is the first time that I can taste the
flavors side by side without having to
book a flight. 32 cups, 16 countries,
all perfectly brewed specialty coffee
prepared [music] in minutes or seconds,
really.
There's a link in the description. You
take $20 off your first order of
Cometeer when you use that link
and you can start tasting the world of
coffee.
>> [music]
[music]